<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Galens bookes of elementes, as they be in the epitome (whiche may very aptly, in my iudgement, be entituled, for the better vnderstanding of the readers, the originall of all thinges naturall in the vvhole vvorlde confuting, as well the errours of all them that went before time, as that hath, or shal folowe hereafter of the Paracelcians : marueilous pleasaunt, and most acceptable for all sharpe wittes, desirous of wisedome) / published foorth of Latine into English, by John Jones ...</title>
            <author>Jones, John, physician.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01417</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24135568_27230</idno>
  <idno type="VID">27230</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264220736</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 11537.3</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S122935</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 420:15 or 1817:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Galens bookes of elementes, as they be in the epitome (whiche may very aptly, in my iudgement, be entituled, for the better vnderstanding of the readers, the originall of all thinges naturall in the vvhole vvorlde confuting, as well the errours of all them that went before time, as that hath, or shal folowe hereafter of the Paracelcians : marueilous pleasaunt, and most acceptable for all sharpe wittes, desirous of wisedome) / published foorth of Latine into English, by John Jones ...</title>
                  <author>Jones, John, physician.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 6 [i.e. 12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By VVilliam Iones, dwelling in Paules Churche yarde, at the southvvest doore of Paules, and are there to be solde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1574.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Based on Galen's De elementis. Cf. NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B4 C2.</note>
                  <note>Pages numbered consecutively on recto only.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 420:15 identified as STC 14725.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27230:1"/>
            <p>❧ <hi>GALENS BOOKES</hi> of Elementes, as they be in the <hi>Epitome (whiche may very aptly, <hi>in my iudgement, be Entituled, for the</hi>
               </hi> better vnderstanding of the Readers, <hi>The Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of all thinges naturall in the vvhole vvorlde: <hi>Confuting, as well the errours of all them that</hi>
               </hi> went before time, as that hath, or shal folowe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after of the <hi>Paracelcians:</hi> marueilous pleasaunt, and most acceptable for all sharpe wittes, desirous of wisedome,) published foorth of Latine into English, <hi>By John Jones, Phisition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶<hi>Jmprinted at London, by</hi> VVilliam Iones, dwelling in Paules <hi>Churche yarde, at the Southvvest doore of Paules, and are there to be solde.</hi> 1574.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27230:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27230:2"/>
            <head>❧ TO THE RIGHT honourable, and moste trustie Earle, <hi>George, Earle of Shrewsbury Earle Marshal of England,</hi> Lorde Talbot, Furniuall, Ʋarden, and Straunge of Blacke Mire, Knight of the most honourable order of the Garter, and one of the Lordes of the Queenes Maiesties moste honourable Priuie Counsell, and Justice in Oyer from Trent Northvvarde &amp;c. John Jones vvisheth al health vvith daily encrease of honour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ippocrates, thauctor and parent preordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Goddes diuine prouidence, for the helthe, welthe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifite of all mankynd, whose wordes, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthorities we admitte, receiue, and allowe, together with <hi>Galen,</hi> as Oracles from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, seemeth vnto me, most noble Earle, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue written rashely, as diuers did of olde, nor yet vnprobably, as other haue of late, wherof I haue made mention in my dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of the natural beginning of all gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing, and liuing thinges, &amp;c. But rather
<pb facs="tcp:27230:3"/> moste diuinely, and Philosophically in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating of the Elementes of mans life, Fire, Ayre, Water, Earthe, omitting with Hipp. the moste simple,<note place="margin">Libr. de Carnibus.</note> not receiuing these foure qualities, <hi>vt Coelum, Spherae, Stellae, Planetae,</hi> as Heauen, Spheres, Starres, and Planets, entreateth here of those simple bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the Elementes, receiuers of the foure qualities, whiche be the beginners of all thinges vnder the Moone: whether they be <hi>Inanimata,</hi> without life, and imperfectly mixt, as the Meteors, or pefectly, as the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, or <hi>Animata,</hi> with life, <hi>Vegetat, sensit, &amp; Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal,</hi> growing thinges, as Hearbes, Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and Trees, &amp;c. Liuing thinges, as Beastes, Foules, and Fishe, and reasonable, as Mankinde, all hauing their originall of the Elementes, not of things void of sense, and vnsufferable, neither of thinges with sense, and vnsufferable: not of the first Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, Suffering, and feeling: neither of thinges suffering without sense, but of the foure Elementes, Fire, Ayre, Water, Earthe, as a Language of an Alphabet,
<pb facs="tcp:27230:3"/> and not of one Elemēt, more then this word (Iohn) can consist of one letter (I.) alone. The whiche olde Hipp. righte aduisedly dooth approoue, writing after this maner:<note place="margin">In Lib. de nat. homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</note>
               <hi>Qui obsecro fieri potest, vt ex vno quicquam consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuatur, quum ne ex pluribus quidem possit, nisi ea pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be fuerint contemperata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How can it be, I pray you, that any thing may of one thing be compounded, seeing of many thinges it cannot, except they be well tempered: comprising briefely and most pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily the summe of the mater.</p>
            <p>The nature, propertie, maner of min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling, and diuisions, as wee haue very brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled in our Tables of Bathes aide, to the prudent Earle of Penbrooke, your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours Sonne in Lawe: so be they at large taught of Galen, in both his bookes (de E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementis.) And do now dedicate them vnto your Noblenesse, as a perpetuall argument of my faitheful and constāt seruice towardes your Lordship, for a presente of this newe yeare: emboldened and animated the rather so to doo, because it is manifeste, as well of Buckstones Bathes benifite, as also by the
<pb facs="tcp:27230:4"/> worthy acceptation of my preseruatiue wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that your hon̄our doth not a litle esteme: rewarde, and commende them that take any small paine in setting foorth that whiche may profite the posterities, as these workes of the very principles of al Philosophie and Phisicke, and therefore thereunto to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed: the argument whereof further to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late vnto your puissaunce, sholde be insteede of a preamble, (perhaps) meere tediousnes, the graue affaires of our weightie and most mightie state, whiche you further so nobly, vigilantly, and faithfully (according to the Prouerbe, with tooth and nayle) considered, the whiche state, God, I beseeche, in all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie long to continue: Oh ingenious head, fraught full of alveritie: Oh godly breast, preseruer of all tranquilitie: Oh inuincible, and soueraigne harte, Elizabeth, daughter of the victorius, and triumphant Henry the eighte.</p>
            <p>Thus, hoping that these workes by vs pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished should seme any lesse englished (albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it) rightly <hi>Ad Verbū, &amp; Sensum,</hi> then with Sir
<pb facs="tcp:27230:4"/> Andr. Lacunae Knighte, Doctour of Phisicke, (in Latine abridged forth of the Greeke) that your Honour of your accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed lenitie wil enterprete it to the best, equall to whom in liberalitie, I knowe fewe, in fidelitie fewer, in affabilitie none.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordshippes alwaies to commaunde, John Jones.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="excerpt">
            <pb facs="tcp:27230:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27230:5"/>
            <head>❧ Galeni Pergameni, de Elementis Liber primus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing that an Element is the leaste portion of the thing whiche it ordayneth, neyther is that same it which is séene in déede, very small, it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festlye appeareth, that the sense is not a Iudge of them whiche be the very Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, according to the very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of euery thing. Therefore wée with <hi>Hipp.</hi> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passing those which be firste in the iudgement of sense, and moste simple, will enquire for those, whiche are in déede Elementes of mans life, and whiche can not bée dissolued into other: and bo no lesse necessarye to cure sicknesses, then those whiche to the sense séeme suche: that is, whether it be one truely in kinde, or els more, and vnlike. If so be, that they be not onely one, but moe, and diuers Elementes, wée muste séeke againe how many they be, as what, and of what sort, and what fellowship they haue together. Therefore, that the first Element, of which both our bodyes, and also the bodies of all other doo consiste, is not one, eyther in fourme or power, <hi>Hipp.</hi> teacheth by this reason.</p>
            <p>If a man were one thing, he shoulde not be gréeued, and if so be he were gréeued, it shoulde require one and onely medicine, comprising wel and briefly the summe of the mater. For if a man were one thing that is fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of one Element, there shoulde be nothing, through whiche he should féele payne.</p>
            <p>If so be that he were afflicted with any griefe, there were but one waye, and one medicine to cure him. For when as he coulde not be hurte through any outwarde
<pb facs="tcp:27230:6"/> cause, it ought necessarily to suffer inwardly of his own nature. And when as there is one onely nature of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, there shalbe one affecte, and the waye to returne to the naturall state, shalbe one: whiche is a verye ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surditie, seeing there be infinite kindes, as well of sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, as of remedyes. By the same reason also you may reprooue the reasons of them, whiche haue brought in, that <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tes without all qualitie, and alteration, and also bodyes vnmade, to be the beginning of all genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For a man shoulde not be gréeued, if his nature were such, séeing that it is necessary, that it which grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, shoulde be a receyuer both of sense and alteration.</p>
            <p>If so be, that it be without all alteration, it will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye kéepe the same state, whiche it had from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. And nowe if it be chaunged, and yet there be not in it naturall power of féeling, it can nothing more féele the affections; then stoanes doo féele.</p>
            <p>Therefore, séeing that bothe these are required in these chaungings, and in bodyes truely, if wée did grow eyther of them, or any suche like, or vnifourme nature, wée shoulde not be gréeued. Therefore wée truely are not made of any vnifourme, or simple substance. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, séeing there be two instrumentes, by whiche all opinions be founde out, that is, reason, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Neither of these wil so serue them, that they shal finde any thing made of them, whiche are altogether impatible or vnsufferable, and without sense, whiche after wil be suffering and partaker of feeling. Nay ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, although al those motes had an ingraffed sense, and were impatible, and not able to be pierced, so that of the onely mutuall ioyning of them, the fleshe it selfe should be engendred. Neuerthelesse, wée shoulde not féele a néedle impacte, or pricte any more, then when wee sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the fingers ioyned therewith. Therfore it resteth, that a féeling bodye shoulde eyther be of those, whiche likewise haue force to féele and suffer, or of those whiche
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27230:6"/> can suffer, but after haue no sense</p>
            <p>And wée will weigh anone whether of these is true: If therefore an Elemente cannot be impatible, it also shal not be one in kinde. If so be, that which is one, is alwaye vnsufferable, séeing there is nothing left, into which it may be chaunged, or of which it may suffer, for whatsoeuer is chaunged, is chaunged into an other, and that which suffereth, suffereth through an other. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, séeing it is nowe prooued, that there be many Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, let vs enquire for the number of them: yet first let vs distinguish the sectes of them, whiche vniuersally dispute of Elementes: for they are brought into foure. The firste of whiche, is that whiche he pronounceth to consiste of thinges voyde of sense, and also vnsuffera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The other whiche consisteth of thinges indewed with sense, but yet vnsufferable: whiche be subiecte to alteration. Both which in this doe agrée, that they both stande of thinges vnsufferable. Wherfore, séeing they teache them to be vnpossible, let vs let them passe.</p>
            <p>There be therefore behinde two: the one, whiche constituteth a féeling bodye, of the firste Elementes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing facultie both of suffering and féeling: An other of thinges suffering, but without sense, both agreeing, that they consist of thinges sufferable: betwéene eyther of whiche sectes, what possible thing doth it contayne. For if you wil trye, and examine by reason the partes, those whiche be of bodyes, hauing power of féeling. If so be, that you shall trye the first elementes, it may easily be, that although they be sayd to haue no sense, so that they can mutually, and manyfoldely doe, and suffer vppon them selues, some bodye endewed with sense, maye be engendred thereof, many particular alterations com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming betwéene. For as oft as any thing is made of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges, if those thinges whiche come into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, suche as they be, shall oure such vnto the ende, that shal neuer attayne any new or purchased fourme,
<pb facs="tcp:27230:7"/> whiche was not before in those thinges of which it was made. But if they many wayes be varied, chaunged, and mingled, then there maye something arise in the thing compounded, whiche may be of an other kinde, to those whiche were founde in the firste Elementes of it. Wherefore, they that will haue a body to be engendred of Fire, Ayre. Water, and Earthe mutually chaunged, and altered, and brought to a certaine temperature en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with a sensitiue facultie, they doe pronounce thinges agréeable vnto truthe.</p>
            <p>But they whiche pronounce of them remaining, as they be, and mingled onely, as Wheate, and Barley, and Beanes are in an heape, they truely doe followe those thinges, whiche can not be done.</p>
            <p>By these therefore it is shewed, that Elementes are moe then one, and also that they can suffer, which <hi>Hipp.</hi> confirming, saith: Howe, I pray you, can it be, that any thing, may of one thing be compounded; séeing of many thinges it can not, except they be well tempered. But whether sensible bodyes doe consiste of the firste Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, in all the whiche there is force of féeling, or of those rather whiche doe wante them, it is not yet she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, that many doo lacke sense, it is thence euidente, that some of the compounde be suche. This therefore is a foolishe opinion, as well of the naturall Philosophers, as of the Phisitions, whiche doo affirme, that there is one Element of man, or of all thinges vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersal. For <hi>Thales, Anaximenus, Anaximandes,</hi> &amp; with them <hi>Heraclitus</hi> doe endeuour to shewe, because of the mutuall alteration of Elementes, they sée all thinges to growe out of kinde, into other that be néere them, euery one of them to be an vniuersall Elemente: yet so that one appoynteth one thing, an other, an other. All the whiche doe séeme to mée, to haue dreamed of that firste mater subiect to all Elementes, whiche they sawe to be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27230:7"/> one: so also they suppose an Element to be one. But they whiche pronounce all thinges to be one thing, do<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> destroye the beginning of natural Philosophie, and also of Phisicke, and therefore against them wée muste not dispute. And this is contrarye to all reason, if because there is seene none of the foure Elementes in the body, pure and sincere, a man woulde denye, that they all are not founde in a man. For why, will you in the bodyes of liuing creatures, finde earth, for example, vnmingled and pure, séeing in the whole, suche cannot be shewed of them: for what soeuer parte of it you shal take, that wil be partaker of suche heate, or humour, and ayre sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunce, yet that earth which wée suppose to be an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is moste thicke, heary, and besides that, colde and drye. If so be, that thou shalt in all the world, shewe me a stoane, an earthy body, truely, I will shewe thee in the bodyes of liuing creatures, some thinges like vnto it, that is, the kinde of boanes, the heares, the gristles, and stoanes. Séeke not therefore in the bodyes of liuing creatures, any thing vnmingled, séeing you shall not finde that in the whole worlde, without counterfeiting. But as often as you shall sée any colde parte drye, and thickie, let it he ynough to call into thy memory, earth, and let it be ynough to behold any moyste thing, thinne and flowing, to conceiue in thy minde water. Also the heate of the liuing creature. Let it present vnto thée Fire, and also the nature of the breath, without the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a liuing body cannot consist, let it bring to your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory firste Ayre, then Fire.</p>
            <p>Neither can you denye, that all fruictes are engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the earth, and of the water, séeing of them they may séeme to haue their beginning, &amp; that they be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Fire, and Ayre tempered vniuersally.</p>
            <p>Hence you maye gather, that if you macerate, or stéepe earth in water, you shal make it nothing but clay, and fruictes be not claye. If therefore fruictes doo take
<pb facs="tcp:27230:8"/> their beginning of the vniuersalitie of Elementes, there is not, why you shoulde doubt of liuing creatures, but that of them they may be nourished.</p>
            <p>Therefore, boldly it is to be professed, that Fire, Water, Ayre, and Earthe, to be the firste, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and moste simple Elementes, and beginniners of all thinges, of whiche verily, both Plantes, and also all liuing creatures, are engendred, nourished, and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, for in them alone you shall finde the chiefest quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, without any mingling, or temperature.</p>
            <p>In Earth, especially colde and drithe, in Fire espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, heate and drithe. In the other, the other qualities, according as euery ones nature dothe require. But to estéeme any Element to be especially moyste, and also to suppose that to be some thing diuers from water, is a pointe of extreme foolishnesse.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, that the especiall heate is simpler then Fire, and that by it added to the mater, the Fire is engendred, it is confessed of all Philosophers, whiche truely dooe confesse vniuersally, that a certaine mater without qualitie, (which is subiecte to all Elementes) and also an especiall heate, which is produced in it, is to Fire the beginning of generation, and also that the mater it selfe, is frée from all generation, &amp; corruption: and the qualitie to be that, whiche in it is bothe engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and perisheth. But an Element in that dothe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from a beginning, that beginnes, shoulde be in the same kinde with those, whose beginninges they be, and Elementes doo alwayes appertayne to the same kinde, for a simple qualitie, is the Elemente of a compounde qualitie, and a simple bodye, of a compounde bodye. Sée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore, hote, moyste, colde, and drye may be thrée wayes saide, that is, either as a qualitie, or els, as an vnmingled bodye, or as that whiche is mingled, and the qualitie not séeme to be an Element, nor yet a mingled or temperate bodye.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:27230:8"/>
            <p>It is too common, that wée saye, an Elemente to be that bodye, whiche is without mingling and tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and also simple of qualitie. Wherefore, at the length we are come necessarily to Fire, Ayre, Water, Earth, in whom firste there is especiall heate, especiall colde, especiall moysture, especiall drithe. Which Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes altogether, or some one alone, we doo common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vse as water, daylye when wée doo drinke, or be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, Ayre, whiche doth enuiron vs, while wée drawe it in by breathing, Fire also, when wée are colde, wee vse that wée may be hote.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, liuing creatures, which eate, eyther sande, earth, stoanes, clay, yea, or boanes, doo plentifully bring earth into their bodyes. Wherfore, I truely doo not sée; why many men doo saye, that neyther Fire, nor Water, nor Ayre, or Earth be taken away, or added to our bodyes, and therfore that they be not Elementes of our bodyes.</p>
            <p>If so be, that any doo therfore thinke, that we do not shewe in our bodyes any Element, because no man is so heated, that he burneth, or drinketh vntil he be burst, they doo not vnderstand, that if one Element doo perishe, the liuing creature likewise perisheth. And the old Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment shall perish, if it be turned: the hote, if it be ouer cooled: the moyste, if it greatly waxe drye: the drye, if it more then méete is, be moystened, Whereupon the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter stādeth otherwise then they think: for alwaies there is eyther some Element added to the body, or els taken away, that which must be moderately done of them that will the liuing creature to be kept sounde: If so be, that immoderate vse of Elements bréedeth to death. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, séeing no qualitie can be founde aparte from sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staunces, wée are compelled to receyue them together with the substaunces, and so to geue them to the bodies, which made them: whiche if they require them especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, wée minister the Elemente it selfe. I saye, Fire,
<pb facs="tcp:27230:9"/> Ayre, Water, Earth. But when a meane qualitie is necessary, we vse a medicine mingled of the Elements, and sometime of a nourishment. Neyther is the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at any time profitable, as a medicine, but when the body néedeth an especiall qualitye. And that <hi>Hipp.</hi> by the name of qualitye doeth vnderstande often times a bodye endued with an especiall qualitye: we maye ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by this saying. If so be where be saieth, when a man dyeth, it is necessarye that euerye part returne to his owne nature, the drye to the drye, the moiste to the moiste, the hote to the hote, the coulde to the coulde. He calleth drye moyste, hote and coulde, not onely quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but also substaunces, in which those qualityes are founde: for those they be whiche the Creature being deade, doe departe, and are mingled to the Elements of vniuersalitye.</p>
            <p>But wee will saye that the qualityes, the Creature being dead, do dye, but not to returne to theyr owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Wherefore there is not why any man any more shoulde goe about to perswade that hée supposeth liuing Creatures to bée begotten of qualities, which can not consist a parte from the bodyes, but of bodies in which those especiall qualityes bée, for they are common Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of all. And those which for any excellencye of these are called Whote, Colde, moyste or dry, are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to euery one.</p>
            <p>A man therfore consisteth of most simple and sensible Elementes, which are called similar, or simple, or lyke. And they againe of the sowre humors, which also doe take their beginnings of things to be eaten and dronke. But these are engendred of Fire, Ayre, Water, and Earth, which truely be constituted of no body any more, but of mater and qualities onely, which we graunt to be the beginnings of them, but not at all the Element: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles the Element hath of the qualities that he is an Element.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:27230:9"/>
            <p>If so be that especiall heate be added, that whole Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men wilbe Fire, and so we must saye of the other thrée qualityes. And of none other qualitie, but of these fowre an Element is iudged.</p>
            <p>But of the proper Elements of Creatures, that is, of humors we must intreate in the next cōmentaries, for of that the similar parts are engendred. These agayne méeting together, that first most simple instrument is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, which for the great function or office of one, is by nature prouduced, then when these are framed together another greater instrument is made, &amp; then the perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the whole body. Therfore that we may repete the whole disputacion, if we be gréeued, our substaunce shal not be one in kinde, nor yet vnsufferable. But wée he gréeued, therefore it shal not be one in kinde, nor suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Againe, if it suffer, it behoued that it heated, cooled, moistened, or dried, should suffer, séeing those which be next cannot by any other meanes be altered. Whole by whole, wherfore it is euident that heate, cold, moisture, &amp; drines, doe constitute or frame the substaunce of euery thing. But how those which are mingled may be ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the whole by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> whole, whether by the only quality, (as <hi>Arist.</hi> supposeth) or whether the substances, they mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually entering into them selues, it is not néedefull for a Phisition to trye. Yet let this suffice to haue spoken in this present, that if wine (for example) be mingled with water, the partes of both these are scattered into the smallest, and by &amp; by, they doe mutually doe and suffer togeather, and so much the easier they do communicate the qualities mutuallye vntill they be brought into lesse through longer mouing and mingling. For in time of necessity the partes of those thinges which are mutually mingled will exactly worke vpon them selues, and exactly suffer, and so all that wilbe one, and on euerye parte like it selfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt">
            <pb facs="tcp:27230:10"/>
            <head>❧ Galeni Pergameni, de Elementis. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Herefore as hote, drye, cold, and moiste are the common Elementes, beginners of all thinges, so Blood, Flegme, &amp; blacke Coler and Yelow are the proper Elements or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of thinges endewed with blood. But proper to men be the similar particles, although these be cōmon to many endewed with blood, as Oxe, Dogge, and Horse, yet not like to men. But ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryly that the partes of all Creatures hauing blood be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred of their mother blood, it is euident inough, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che séeing it is partaker of Flegme, and also of other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler it is shewed, by which reason <hi>Hipp.</hi> perswaded, hath taught that the foure humors be the matter to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender man. Furthermore, Fleshe and Sinowes bée partes similar or simple, and séeing the Fleshe is Blood, and beside softe and hote, but the Sinowe without blood, hard &amp; cold, and also other parts haue other differences. It séemeth agréeable vnto reason, that wise nature at what time shee framed the issue or infant of the mothers blood to haue drawen that which was thicker to consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute sounder bodies, that which was thinner to the sof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that which was hotter to the hotter, that which was colder to the colder.</p>
            <p>And in the time folowing, that euery one of the parts fourmed had his proper Eliment or nourishment, and encrease, of proper and particuler matter, for euen as in Milke there is founde both milke, and also a certaine chéesie substaunce, so in blood you may finde a certaine
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27230:10"/> thinne liquour much like the whea of blood, and also as it were a certaine mudde and beside, the fibres which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken from the blood, as the blood shall no more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, so also it shall in colour bée varied, wherevppon the blood is not simple. Otherwise it shoulde be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies like both in men and beastes. But by experience wée maye knowe the contrarye, bothe of the varietye of colours, and especially of thinges which are euacuated by purging Medicines. Whiche truely if they be well ministred, they wyll drawe vnto them according to the differences of sicknesses iuyces perticular and differing. Against whiche <hi>Asclepiades</hi> endeuoureth to perswade, that is, that the medicines doe not drawe vnto the familiar iuyces, but to chaunge and to corrupt them, and to alter them into theyr owne nature, which truely as they bée most absurde, so those thinges which daylye we sée done by immoderate purgations, doe shewe most euidentlye howe euery medicine doeth drawe their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per humors. If so be that as often as any man hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued a medicine which hath power to clense choler, first it shal expel such humor, by vomitte, after Flegme, then blacke choler, lastly pure blood, which being euacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, the soule departeth. If you giue a medicine dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Flegme, that shall first bée emptied, then Yelowe coler, because, it is easie to be brought forth, after blacke very stubburne and resistyng. And laste of all blood is alway brought foorth because it is set very néere nature.</p>
            <p>Therefore, when that first humor is euacuated, the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Creature cannot then bée in health, when it hath loste one of his Elementes, but it is altogeather dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and perisheth. And then out of the rest there floweth humor which is more fit to bée clensed, because there is a certaine naturall power to euery thing to draw those thinges which be conuenient for it. As in the Loade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone there is force to drawe vnto it Yron. And through this facultye, both nourishmentes and euacuations are
<pb facs="tcp:27230:11"/> made, it drawing alwayes that which is expedient, yet often with this, something which is not expedient, so that sometime it commeth in vse to haue purging medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, which truely when they haue drawen that flegme or coler which doeth abounde, they catche vnto them some peculiar humor of the sounde partes, by a certaine force and dissoluing, and melting them, and bringing them to Elements, and committing the creature to death, and another certaine humor fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the violence of this attraction of affinitye vnto it, which first was drawen by force.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>